Guide to the Tony Towle Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tony Towle papers
1960-2011
YCAL MSS 745
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.29
(17 boxes)
Collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers documenting the life and literary activities of New York City poet Tony Towle. Towle spent his life in New York City and, after training with Kenneth Koch and Frank O'Hara, was associated with the second generation of the New York School. In addition to Koch and O'Hara, Towle corresponded with numerous poets, artists, and editors based in the city, including John Ashberry, Bill Berkson, Ted Berrigan, Joe Brainard, Rob Hershon, Lita Hornick, Sheila Lanham, Charles North, Jeni Olin, Ron Padgett, James Schuyler, David Shapiro, Paul Violi, Anne Waldman, and others.
Towle, Tony, 1939-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 17 (Correspondence): Restricted until 1 January 2028. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from James S. Jaffe Rare Books on the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 2012.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1962-2011. II. Writings, 1960-2010.
Tony Towle (1939-)
Tony Towle was born 13 June 1939 in New York City to Erwin W. and Mary E. (Rigg) Towle. He attended Georgetown University (1957), New York University (1961-1962), Columbia University (1963), and The New School for Social Research (1963-1964). Towle worked as the secretary at Universal Limited Art Editions, a printmaking studio, in West Islip, New York, from 1964 to 1981. His published works include: Poems (1966), After Dinner We Take a Drive Into the Night (1968), North (1970), Autobiography, and Other Poems (1977), Works on Paper (1978), Gemini (1980), New and Selected Poems (1983), Some Musical Episodes (1992), The History of the Invitation: New & Selected Poems (2001), and Winter Journey (2008). Awards include the Gotham Book Mart Avant-Garde Poetry prize (1963), Wagner College Writer's Conference poetry prize (1963), Poet's Foundation awards (1964, 1966), and Frank O'Hara Award (1970) for North.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and other papers documenting the life and literary activities of the American poet Tony Towle. Towle spent the bulk of his life in New York City and, after he started writing poetry in the early 1960s and trained with Kenneth Koch and Frank O'Hara at The New School in 1963, he was associated with the second generation of the New York School. In addition to Koch and O'Hara, Towle corresponded with numerous poets, artists, and editors based in the city, including John Ashbery, Bill Berkson, Ted Berrigan, Joe Brainard, Rob Hershon, Lita Hornick, Sheila Lanham, Charles North, Jeni Olin, Ron Padgett, James Schuyler, David Shapiro, Paul Violi, Anne Waldman, and others.
Writings in the collection consists of drafts and proofs for many of Towle's published works, including Autobiography and Other Poems (1977), Works on Paper (1978), The History of the Invitation (2001), New & Selected Poems (1983), North (1970), Winter Journey (2008), and Memoir (2003). In addition to the material relating to published works, there are drafts for individual poems and prose works, fiction and non-fiction, printed publicity, reviews, royalty statments, permissions, as well as material relating to Towle's employment in the printmaking studio, Universal Limited Art Editions.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Ashbery, John, 1927-2017; Berkson, Bill, 1939-2016; Berrigan, Ted, 1934-1983; Brainard, Joe, 1942-1994; Hershon, Robert, 1936-; Hornick, Lita R., 1927-; Koch, Kenneth, 1925-2002; Lanham, Sheila Mae; North, Charles, 1941-; Olin, Jeni, 1974-; Padgett, Ron, 1942-; Schuyler, James; Shapiro, David, 1947-; Towle, Tony, 1939-; Violi, Paul, 1944-2011; Waldman, Anne, 1945-
- Correspondence, 1962-2011; Series I; 8; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized as received by the library.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence contains five groupings of personal correspondence organized chronologically by date and then alphabetically by name within each grouping. Towle correspondended with numerous poets, artists, and editors based in New York City, including John Ashbery, Bill Berkson, Ted Berrigan, Joe Brainard, Rob Hershon, Lita Hornick, Kenneth Koch, Sheila Lanham, Frank O'Hara, Charles North, Jeni Olin, Ron Padgett, James Schuyler, David Shapiro, Paul Violi, Anne Waldman, and others.
  - 1963-1979
    - "A" general, 1963-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Ashbery, John, 1963-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Ayden, Erje, 1971-1976, undated (Box 1)
    - "B" general, 1965-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Berkson, Bill, 1965-1979 (Box 1)
    - Berrigan, Ted, circa 1963-1979 (Box 1)
    - Brainard, Joe, 1964-1974 (Box 1)
    - "C" general, 1966-1979 (Box 1)
    - Carroll, Paul, 1967-1972 (Box 1)
    - Chaloner, David, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - "D" general, 1963-1974, undated (Box 1)
    - "E" general, 1965-1978 (Box 1)
    - Elmslie, Kenward, 1963-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - "F" general, 1964-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - "G" general, 1967-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Gioseffi, Daniella, 1969-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Golde, Morris, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
    - Goldman, Judith, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - "H" general, 1968-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Haseloff, Charles, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Hornick, Lita, 1964-1979 (Box 1)
    - "I" - "J" general, 1965-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - "K" general, 1964-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Koch, Kenneth, 1966-1970, undated (Box 1)
    - Kornblum, Allan, 1971-1973, undated (Box 1)
    - Kostakis, Peter, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - "L" general, 1967-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Lima, Frank, 1962-2000, undated (Box 1)
    - "M" general, 1963-1979, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - "N" general, 1966-1976, undated (Box 2)
    - North, Charles, 1970-1979; 3 (Box 2)
    - "O" general, 1972-1977, undated (Box 2)
    - O'Hara, Frank, 1950-1978, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - "P" - "Q" general, 1966-1979, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Padgett, Ron, 1964-1978, undated (Box 2)
    - Pittsburgh High Schools, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - "Q" - "R" general, 1964-1979, undated (Box 2)
    - "S" general, 1962-1979, undated (Box 2)
    - Schuyler, James, 1966-1978 (Box 2)
    - "T" general, 1966-1977 (Box 2)
    - "U" - "V" general, 1969-1978 (Box 2)
    - Violi, Paul, 1971-1979 (Box 2)
    - "W" - "Z" general, 1968-1979, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Waldman, Anne, 1967-1979 (Box 2)
  - 1980-2005
    - "A" general, 1987-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Ashbery, John, 1982-2002 (Box 3)
    - "B" general, 1979-2005 (Box 3)
    - Berkson, Bill, 2001-2004 (Box 3)
    - Bolton, Ken, 1993-2003, undated (Box 3)
    - Brennan, Max; Burton, Sigrid, 1982-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - "C" general, 1981-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Cohen, Mo, 1981-2005 (Box 3)
    - Collins, Billy, 1989-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - "D" general, 1981-2005 (Box 3)
    - "E" general, 1982-2003 (Box 3)
    - Edelstein, Leo, 2000-2005 (Box 3)
    - "F" general, 1989-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Fossella, Darrin, 2003-2004, undated (Box 3)
    - Friedman, Ed, 1986-2003, undated (Box 3)
    - "G" general, 1982-2002 (Box 3)
    - "H" general, 1969-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Hershon, Bob, 1989-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Holabird, Jean, 1980-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - "I" - "J" general, 1981-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Jamail, Justin, 2002-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Jensen, Ruth, 1994-1998, undated (Box 3)
    - Jimenez, Vita, 1993-2005, undated; 2 (Box 3)
    - "K" general, 1983-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Kelley, David, 1980-2005, undated (Box 3)
    - Kimball, Jack, 1998-2005 (Box 4)
    - Koch, Kenneth, 1982-2005, undated (Box 4)
    - "L" general, 1978-2005, undated (Box 4)
    - Lima, Frank, 1993-1997 (Box 4)
    - "M" general, 1981-2005, undated (Box 4)
    - Maurer, Susan, 1996-1997, undated (Box 4)
    - McCain, Gillian, 1958-2005, undated (Box 4)
    - "N" - "O" general, 1980-2005, undated (Box 4)
    - North, Charles, 1980-2005; 2 (Box 4)
    - Olin, Jeni, 2001-2005; 2 (Box 4)
    - "P" - "Q" general, 1979-2005 (Box 4)
    - Padgett, Ron, 1982-2005 (Box 4)
    - Perry, David, 2003-2005 (Box 4)
    - Poetry Project, 1980-2004 (Box 4)
    - Poetry Project Newsletter, 1988-1989; 2 (Box 4)
    - "R" general, 1985-2005, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Riggins, Roger, 1982 (Box 4)
    - "S" general, 1980-2005, undated (Box 4)
    - Salerno, Mark, 1993-2001, undated (Box 4)
    - Sawyer, Larry, 1998-2005 (Box 4)
    - Somerville, Michele, 2004-2005; 2 (Box 4)
    - Stannard, Martin, 1983-2001, undated (Box 5)
    - "T" - "U" general, 1980-2003, undated (Box 5)
    - Tranter, John, 1999-2005 (Box 5)
    - Tyler, Diane, 1998-2005 (Box 5)
    - "V" general, 1980-2005, undated (Box 5)
    - Violi, Paul, 1955-2005, undated; 3 (Box 5)
    - "W" general, 1979-2004, undated (Box 5)
    - Waldman, Anne, 1983-2000 (Box 5)
    - Wasserman, Jo Ann, 2001-2005 (Box 5)
    - Website, 2004-2005, undated (Box 5)
    - The World submissions, 1980 (Box 5)
    - "X" - "Z" general, 1980-2005, undated (Box 5)
  - 2006-2009
    - "A" general, 2005-2008 (Box 5)
    - "B" general, 2007-2009 (Box 5)
    - Barile, Susan; Gaffney, John, 2006-2009 (Box 5)
    - Berkson, Bill, 2008-2009; 2 (Box 5)
    - Berrigan, Anselm, 2006 (Box 5)
    - Best American Poetry, 2006 (Box 5)
    - Bolton, Ken, 2006-2008 (Box 5)
    - Brook, Donna, 2006-2009 (Box 5)
    - "C" general, 2006-2009 (Box 5)
    - "D" general, 2006-2008 (Box 5)
    - Davis, Michael, 2006-2009; 2 (Box 5)
    - DeCreeft, Donna, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Di Rifiuti, Isola, 2008 (Box 5)
    - "E" general, 2007-2008 (Box 5)
    - EPC website, 2007-2008 (Box 5)
    - "F" general, 2006-2009 (Box 5)
    - "G" general, 2007-2009 (Box 5)
    - Goldenberg, Tom, 2007-2009 (Box 5)
    - "H" general, 2007-2009 (Box 5)
    - Hershon, Bob, 2006-2009; 2 (Box 6)
    - Holabird, Jean, 2005-2009 (Box 6)
    - Holman, Bob, 2006-2007 (Box 6)
    - Horning, Ron, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - "I" - "J" general, 2007-2009 (Box 6)
    - Jamail, Justin, 2006-2009, undated (Box 6)
    - Jimenez, Vita, 2006-2009; 2 (Box 6)
    - "K" general, 2006-20009, undated (Box 6)
    - Kaplan, Allan, 2007-2009 (Box 6)
    - Kelley, David, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - Kimball, Jack, 2006-2008 (Box 6)
    - Koch, Karen, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - "L" general, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - Lanham, Sheila, 2009 (Box 6)
    - Latta, John, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - "M" general, 2006-2008, undated (Box 6)
    - Maurer, Susan, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - McCain, Gillian, 2006-2009, undated (Box 6)
    - McCarron, Andrew, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - "N" - "O" general, 2007-2009 (Box 6)
    - North, Charles, 2006-2009; 5 (Box 6)
    - O'Hara, Frank, 2006-2009, undated (Box 6)
    - Olin, Jeni, 2006-2007 (Box 6)
    - "P" - "Q" general, 2006-2009, undated (Box 6)
    - Padgett, Ron, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - "R" general, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - Reed, Monica, 2006-2009 (Box 6)
    - Roberts, Steve, 2006-2008 (Box 6)
    - "S" general, 2001-2009, undated (Box 7)
    - Schmall, Jeremy, 2008-2009 (Box 7)
    - Shapiro, David, 2006 (Box 7)
    - Somerville, Michele, 2006-2009; 4 (Box 7)
    - St. Mark's Workshop, 2006 (Box 7)
    - Szymaszek, Stacy, 2007-2009 (Box 7)
    - "T" general, 2007-2009 (Box 7)
    - Tyler, Diane, 2006-2009; 2 (Box 7)
    - "U" - "V" general, 2006-2009 (Box 7)
    - Violi, Paul, 2006-2009; 2 (Box 7)
    - "W" general, 2006-2009 (Box 7)
    - "X" - "Z" general, 2007-2009 (Box 7)
    - Zoland Books, 2006-2007, undated (Box 7)
  - 2010
    - "A" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "B" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "C" general, 2010-2011 (Box 7)
    - "D" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - DeCreeft, Donna, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "E" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "F" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "G" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "H" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "I" - "J" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "K" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "L" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "M" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "N" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - North, Charles, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "O" - "Q" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - O'Hara, Maureen, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "R" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "S" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "T" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "U" - "V" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - Violi, Paul, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "W" general, 2010 (Box 7)
    - "X" - "Z" general, 2010 (Box 7)
  - 2011
    - "A" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "B" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "C" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "D" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "E" - "F" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "G" - "H" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - Goldston, Andrea, 2011 (Box 8)
    - Hart, Matt, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "I" - "J" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "K" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "L" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "M" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "N" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - North, Charles, 2011; 3 (Box 8)
    - "O" - "P" general, 2010-2011 (Box 8)
    - "Q" - "R" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "S" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "T" - "U" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - Violi, Paul, 2011 (Box 8)
    - Violi Reading, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "V" - "W" general, 2011 (Box 8)
    - "X" - "Z" general, 2011 (Box 8)
- Writings, 1960-2010; Series II; 7; (7 boxes)
  Files are not arranged in any particular order.
  Series II. Writings contains drafts and proofs for many of Towle's published works, including files for Autobiography and Other Poems (1977), Works on Paper (1978), The History of the Invitation (2001), New & Selected Poems (1983), North (1970), Winter Journey (2008), and Memoir (2003). In addition to the materials relating to published works, there are drafts for individual poems and prose works, fiction and non-fiction, printed publicity, reviews, royalty statments, permissions, and material relating to Towle's employment in the printmaking studio, Universal Limited Art Editions.
  - MS, 1960-1962; 2 (Box 9)
  - Poems, misc. typescripts, 1960-1962 (Box 9)
  - Poems, 1960-1964; 6 (Box 9)
  - "Lines for the New Year", 1963-1965; 3 (Box 9)
  - Poems, 1965-1969; 2 (Box 9)
  - Notes, 1970-1971 (Box 9)
  - "The Sea and the Wind", 1970-1971 (Box 9)
  - "Nearing Xmas", 1970-1971 (Box 9)
  - Poems, 1970-1972; 2 (Box 9)
  - "In the Romantic Manner", 1970 (Box 10)
  - "Pencils and Postcards", 1978 (Box 10)
  - Misc. visual, 1974-1976 (Box 10)
  - New York 7/29/72, 1975 (Box 10)
  - 1977 collabs (Box 10)
  - "The Interesting Story", 1974 (Box 10)
  - Gemini, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Autobiography and Other Poems, 1970-1974; 4 (Box 10)
  - Works on Paper, 1970-1974; 2 (Box 10)
  - Swinburne, 1972-1974 (Box 10)
  - Poems, 1972-1974; 2 (Box 10)
  - Sketches, 1973-1975 (Box 10)
  - Drafts, 1973-1979; 4 (Box 10)
  - Towle-publications, 1963-2010 (Box 11)
  - "Complete Poems", 1963-2009; 5 (Box 11)
  - Drafts-1980's, 1980-1989 (Box 11)
  - Drafts-1990's, 1990-1999; 2 (Box 11)
  - Storytelling, undated (Box 11)
  - Postmod. maturity, undated (Box 11)
  - Foundations, 1971-2006 (Box 11)
  - Rejections, 1965-1991 (Box 11)
  - Rejections of Autobiography, 1972-1975 (Box 11)
  - Immaterial Nocturnes, 2001-2008 (Box 11)
  - Gemini, 2001-2008 (Box 11)
  - Illuminations, 2001-2008 (Box 11)
  - Drafts, 2001-2008 (Box 11)
  - Winter Journey, 2001-2008 (Box 11)
  - Permissions, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Royalty statements, 1964-1970 (Box 11)
  - Poetic income, 1971-1979 (Box 11)
  - Columbia U. Press, 1960-1990 (Box 11)
  - Consignment, 1970-1979 (Box 11)
  - Young Am. Poets, 1960-1990 (Box 11)
  - Winter Journey, 1999-2007; 5 (Box 12)
  - Wagner College, 1963 (Box 12)
  - New School, 1963 (Box 12)
  - Nine Immaterial Nocturnes, 2003 (Box 12)
  - The History of the Invitation; New & Selected Poems 1963-2000, 2001; 5 (Box 12)
  - New & Selected Poems (1963-1983), undated; 7 (Box 12)
  - North, proofs, undated (Box 13)
  - North correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - Poetry workshop, 1969-2003; 3 (Box 13)
  - Poems - 1966 (Box 13)
  - Poems, 1963-1979; 7 (Box 13)
  - Collaborations, undated (Box 13)
  - "Lines for the New Year", 1964-1973 (Box 13)
  - Towle readings, 1963-2012 (Box 13)
  - Reviews, intros, etc., 1960-1969 (Box 13)
  - Anouncements, 1960-2006; 5 (Box 13)
  - Reviews, 1970-2010; 6 (Box 14)
  - Mentions, 2002-2008 (Box 14)
  - Misc. art reviews, etc., 1970-1990, undated (Box 14)
  - "Truth in Advertising", undated (Box 14)
  - Some Musical Episodes, undated (Box 14)
  - Poetic income, 1963-1977 (Box 14)
  - Prose (fiction), 1964-1979; 3 (Box 14)
  - Prose (non-fiction), 1971-2007; 2 (Box 14)
  - Memoir, undated; 3 (Box 14)
  - Bontecou notes, undated (Box 14)
  - Bontecou interview, 1970 (Box 14)
  - TT, ZP, BG re: 18 cantos, 1967 July 25 (Box 14)
  - ULAE interview, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Text for Grosman's posthumous NYU show, undated (Box 15)
  - TT writings/int ULAE, 1966 (Box 15)
  - TT/L rivers, 1977 June 24 (Box 15)
  - ULAE diary, 1975-1978; 7 (Box 15)
  - ULAE outline, 1979 (Box 15)
  - ULAE text, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Castleman books, undated (Box 15)
  - Corcoran memoir, 1996 (Box 15)
  - Corcoran gallery, 1996-1998 (Box 15)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Announcements (In Series II), 1970-2005 (Box 16)
  - Reviews (In Series II), 1970-2001 (Box 16)
- Restricted Material, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 17 (Correspondence): Restricted until 1 January 2028. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 17)
    Restricted until 1 January 2028. For further information consult the appropriate curator.